Guide to the Margaret Sartor Photographs and Papers, 1966-2003 RL.01139
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Margaret Sartor photographs and papers
1966-2003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sartor, Margaret
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
RL.01139
14.5 Linear Feet
545 Items
Margaret Sartor is a photographer and instructor at Duke University's Center for Documentary Studies. Her Photographs and Papers collection includes photographs of the American South, and some materials from her book project on William Gedney.
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted for exhibition and some reproduction. Contact Research Services staff for further information.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Margaret Sartor Photographs and Papers were received by the Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library in 2001, 2002, 2003, and 2015.
Biographical Note
Documentary photographer and instructor at the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University.
Collection Overview
The 2001 Accession (2001-0074) (260 items; 9 lin. ft.; dated 1985-2000) contains black-and-white prints (16x20 and 11x14) by Sartor, focusing especially on home, family, and suburban life in the American South.
The 2002 addition (02-083) (38 items, 3 lin. ft.; dated 1984-2001) contains thirty-eight 16x20 black-and-white photographs printed by Sartor in 2001 from negatives shot 1984-2001. Focus is on home, family, and suburban life in the American South.
The 2003 addition (03-121) (47 items, 1.5 lin. ft.; dated 1987-2003) comprises forty-seven exhibition quality black-and-white 16x20 prints by Sartor, shot between 1987 and 2003, but mostly printed in 2002 and 2003. Subjects include women and family in the suburban South.
The 2015 addition consists of materials relating to Sartor's book, What Was True: The Photographs and Notebooks of William Gedney, published in 2000. This materials has been arranged into a Book Projects series.
Related Material
The Margaret Sartor Photographs in the Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library may contain related material to the Margaret Sartor Papers in the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture, which is closed to research.
Duke University -- Faculty; Black-and-white photographs; Documentary Photography; Southern States -- Social conditions; Southern States -- Photographs; Suburban life -- Southern States -- Pictorial works; Southern States -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Family-Southern States; Suburban life -- Southern States; Sartor, Margaret; Gedney, William, -1989; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
- Accession (2001-0074), 1985-2000, 10 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Accession (260 items; 9 lin. ft.) contains black-and-white prints (16x20 and 11x14) by Sartor, focusing especially on home, family, and suburban life in the American South.
  - Photographs: Family and close friends, 1986-1989 (Box 1)
  - Photographs: The South/general, 1986-1989 (Box 2)
  - Photographs: Monroe, LA and nearby towns and area, 1986-1989 (Box 3)
  - Photographs, 1985-1989 (Box 4)
  - Photographs, 1990-1992 (Box 5)
  - Photographs, 1993 (Box 6)
  - Photographs, 1994 (Box 7)
  - Photographs, 1995-1996 (Box 8)
  - Photographs, 1997-1998 (Box 9)
  - Photographs, 1999 (Box 10)
  - Photographs, 2000 (Box 11)
- Accession (2002-0083), 1984-2001, 1 box
  Addition (38 items, 3 lin. ft.) contains thirty-eight, 16x20, black-and-white photographs printed by Sartor in 2001 from negatives shot 1984-2001. Focus is on home, family, and suburban life in the American South.
  - Photographs, 1984-2001 (Box 12)
- Accession (2003-0121), 1987-2003, 3 boxes
  Addition (47 items, 1.5 lin. ft.) comprises forty-seven, exhibition quality, black-and-white 16x20 prints by Sartor, shot between 1987 and 2003, but mostly printed in 2002 and 2003. Subjects include women and family in the suburban South.
  - Photographs, 1994-2003 (Box 13)
  - Photographs, 1994-2003 (Box 14)
  - Photographs, 1987-1999 (Box 15)
- Exhibit prints, 2006, 2 boxes
  Matted prints exhibited at Duke University in 2006 under the title "Close to Home: Photographs by Margaret Sartor," and now part of an online exhibit. Prints were selected from previously accessioned material listed above.
  - Eleven 16x20 gelatin silver prints in 20x24 mats (Box 16)
    - Wood blocks, Monroe, LA, 1993 (Box 16)
    - Fellowship Hall, Monroe, LA, 1989 (Box 16)
    - Morgan on Easter afternoon, Monroe, LA, 1998 (Box 16)
    - Dorothy with her boyfriend, Monroe, LA, 1994 (Box 16)
    - Big Ryan, Monroe, LA, 1999 (Box 16)
    - Gus on mother's patio, Monroe, LA, 1997 (Box 16)
    - Homemade Jesus billboard near Alto, LA, 1986 (Box 16)
    - Big Ryan, family wedding reception, Monroe, LA, 1993 (Box 16)
    - Backyard with birdbath, Monroe, LA, 1993 (Box 16)
    - Dixie Deb Softball League Game, Monroe, LA, 1987 (Box 16)
    - Kelley on the balcony, Gulf Shores, AL, 1994 (Box 16)
  - Eleven 16x20 gelatin silver prints in 20x24 mats (Box 17)
    - Sunday School classroom, Monroe, LA, 1993 (Box 17)
    - Little Ryan on the telephone, Monroe, LA, 1986 (Box 17)
    - Morgan with her father, Gulf Shores, AL, 1994 (Box 17)
    - Morgan at the Crawfish Boil, Monroe, LA, 1997 (Box 17)
    - Will with bubble wand, Monroe, LA, 2000 (Box 17)
    - Morgan, Monroe, LA, 1993 (Box 17)
    - Emily as catcher, Monroe, LA, 1988 (Box 17)
    - Emily at Gulf Shores, AL, 1987 (Box 17)
    - Trey holding Casey's hand on the levee, Monroe, LA, 2002 (Box 17)
    - Katherine in the playhouse built for her by ther father, Monroe, LA, 1989 (Box 17)
    - Emily in the garden, Monroe, LA, 1999 (Box 17)
- Book Projects, 1964-2001
  - What Was True: The Photographs and Notebooks of William Gedney, 1966-2001
    Scope and Contents
    Materials related to the research and publication of Sartor's book, What Was True: The Photographs and Notebooks of William Gedney, published by W.W. Norton in 2000.
    - Correspondence re: David Roche, 2000-2001 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - David Roche "green notebook" photocopies, 1966-1967 (Box 18, Folder 2)
      Photocopied in 2000.
    - David Roche text, "Green Notebook #1", undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
      Photocopied 1997.
    - Gedney Interviews, 2 folders (Box 18, Folder 4-5)
      Various interviews with people close to Gedney. First folder contains names (B-M), second folder contains names (O-S).
    - Gedney Slides 1-3 (Binder 1), 1996; 3 folders (Box 18, Folder 6-8)
      3 folders of slides made from Gedney photographs, originally from Sartor's Binder 1.
    - Gedney Slides 4-6 (Binder 2), 1996-1999; 3 folders (Box 19, Folder 1-3)
      3 folders of slides made from photographs by Gedney, numbered Folder 4-7; originally from Sartor's Binder 2.
    - Gedney Slides 7 (Binder 2), 1964-1980 (Box 19, Folder 4)
      Folder 4 of Binder 2 contains pictures and outline of images used in "What Was True"
    - Short Distances and Definite Places, Photographs and Notebooks of William Gedney page proofs, 1998 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - What Was True: Photographs and Notebooks of William Gedney page proofs, 1999 (Box 20, Folder 2)